Finding Aid for the Albert H. and Emma M. Wheeler papers 1938-1994 (bulk 1960-1977)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Mayoral Files 1975-1978
  Mayor Wheeler served in a dual capacity at hearings before the Science, Research and Technology Subcommittee of the House of Representatives in 1977. He offered testimony on DNA research from his unique perspective as a mayor representing concerned citizens, and as a microbiologist. These materials are located in the DNA Research file.
  This series concludes with several folders of clippings that concern themselves with general issues, as well as the elections of 1975, 1977, and 1978. The 1977 election, in which Wheeler won by one vote captured national media attention. Also included is campaign literature distributed by Albert Wheeler in his quest for office.
  - Administration
    - Mayoral Election
      - 1975 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
    - Mayor's Vetoes 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Proclamations 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Press Releases 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Reports and Communications to Council 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Resolutions 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Speeches and Remarks 1976-1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence
    - Citizen Requests, Community Development Revenue Sharing (CDRS) 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Complaints 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Congratulatory 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Federal Legislation 1976-1977 (Box 4)
    - General 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Memos 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - National League of Cities 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Outgoing 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - State Legislation 1975-1977 (Box 4)
    - Thank You 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - White House 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - Airport 1977 (Box 4)
    - Airport Advisory Commission 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor/Pittsfield Drain and Flooding 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Railroad 1975 (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Street Art Fair 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Ann Arbor Transportation Authority, (aatA) 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Anti-Rape Advisory Board 1974-1976 (Box 5)
    - Assessor 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Assistant City Administrator 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Attorney 1977 (Box 5)
    - Bicentennial Commission 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Blue Magic" Incident 1975 (Box 5)
    - Boards and Commissions 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Budget 1975 (Box 5)
    - Cablecasting Commission 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Campaign Literature undated (Box 5)
    - Citizen's Recreation Advisory Commission 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - City Administrator 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - City Council 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - City-University 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Community Development 1975 (Box 5)
    - Community Development Block Grant (CDBG) and Community Development Resource Sharing (CDRS) 1975-1980 (Box 5)
    - Community Planning and Management 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Compensation Commission 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Comprehensive Employment Training Act (CETA) 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Controller Investment Crisis 1977 (Box 5)
    - Democratic Budget Proposal 1975 (Box 5)
    - DNA Research 1977 (Box 5)
    - Dean, Elizabeth Fund 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Employees Retirement System 1976 (Box 5)
    - Fair Rental Practices Commission 1975 (Box 5)
    - Fire Department 1976 (Box 5)
    - Historic District Commission 1977 (Box 5)
    - House Bill No. 6010, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Housing Commission 1977 (Box 5)
    - Human Rights Commission 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Human Rights Department 1977 (Box 5)
    - Human Services Department 1975 (Box 5)
    - Huron View Heights Development 1975 (Box 5)
    - International Exchange/Sister Cities 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Investment Committee 1977 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Municipal League 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Model Cities 1975 (Box 5)
    - National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health Facility (NIOSHA) 1977 (Box 5)
    - 911 Emergency System 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Old West Side Historic District Commission 1976 (Box 5)
    - Ozone House 1975 (Box 5)
    - Parks Concerts (Summers) 1975 (Box 5)
    - Parking Facilities Commission 1976 (Box 5)
    - Parks and Open Spaces 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Parks and Recreation 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Pet Control Commission 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Planning Commission 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Planning Department 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Police Department 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Post Office Purchase 1977 (Box 5)
    - Preferential Voting 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Problems of the Handicapped Committee 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Public Works 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Public Works Department 1976-1978 (Box 5)
    - Pump-N-Pantry Incident 1976 (Box 5)
    - Sign Ordinance 1975 (Box 5)
    - Southeast Michigan Council of Governments (SEMCOG) 1976-1977 (Box 5)
    - Streets, Traffic, and Parking 1975-1978 (Box 5)
    - Super Sewer A-95 Review 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan / AFSCME Strike 1977 (Box 5)
    - Utilities 1975-1977 (Box 5)
    - Voter Registration (door to door) 1975 (Box 5)
    - Want Squad-Drug Raid 1975 (Box 5)
    - Weapons Policy 1976 (Box 5)
    - Zoning Board of Appeals 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Clippings
    - General 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Election 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
- University of Michigan 1962-1990
  The University of Michigan series (1962-1990; 3 inches) is quite small, often focusing on Wheeler's unique role as the first African-American tenured faculty member. His perspective on issues involving race and university policy was often sought.
  - Black Action Movement Conference 1990 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence 1964-1990 (Box 6)
  - Diversity Day 1989 (Box 6)
  - Faculty/Staff Committee 1967 (Box 6)
  - Medical School 1962-1970 (Box 6)
  - Medical School Admissions Policy 1986 (Box 6)
  - Opportunity Awards Committee 1966 (Box 6)
  - Steering Committee on Academic Opportunities 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Tuskegee Institute 1966 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (2 inches) primarily includes photographs taken while Wheeler was mayor of the city of Ann Arbor. A small number of NAACP photographs document that organization, including the march from Benton Harbor to St. Joseph. The photographs are undated and do not include any information about other persons in them.
  - Mayoral, NAACP and march from St. Joseph to Benton Harbor (Box 6)
- Medical 1957-1980
  The Medical series (1957-1980; .5 linear feet) consists of material Wheeler collected and created while he was a professor of microbiology in the Medical School of the University of Michigan. Most of this pertains to his teaching responsibilities at the university and includes lectures, slides, and lab assignments. The remainder is a miscellanea of other medically-related material such as correspondence, reports of experiments, and writings.
  - Correspondence 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Lectures, audio cassette and slides undated, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Notes 1968 (Box 6)
  - Records of Experiments 1957-1968, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Teaching Material
    - Clinical Medicine 600 1970 (Box 6)
    - Fundamentals of Immunology 1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Medical Technology 1969 (Box 6)
    - Microbiology
      - 424 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - 620 1967 (Box 6)
      - 620 1980, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Public Health
      - 500 1970 (Box 6)
      - 501 1967 (Box 6)
  - Writings 1966 (Box 6)